# **Ali Dorosty**

Sydney, Australia

m dorosty.github.io/website

in linkedin.com/in/ali-dorosty

Experienced **front-end & Node.js developer** with a strong background in interactive UI projects and a deep understanding of JavaScript. Demonstrates advanced coding techniques, including custom interactions and animations, managing complicated concurrent activities, and proficient functional programming. Passionate about delving into the inner workings of technology and creating from scratch. Honed skills since starting as a hobbyist coder in JavaScript in college in 2013.

## **Experience**

#### Freelance Work

Jan 2022 - Current

#### **Divar**

Apr 2019 - Sep 2021

#### Senior Front-End Developer

2 years

- Worked with cross-functional teams to implement new features and collaborated with 8-10 people in developing the responsive front end for the popular e-commerce website <a href="https://divar.ir">https://divar.ir</a>.
  - Deployed large scale website with complex Redux state management and SSR to production facing 50+ million users as a system owner.
  - Reviewed merge requests, mentored a newly hired developer, and interviewed potential candidates as part of the team's hiring process.
- Reimplemented & modernized critical legacy custom Node.js server & middleware code for server-side rendering, SEO, request caching, and error logging.
- Refactored a general-purpose React component responsible for dynamically generating forms based on specifications described in the JSON schema format, while also adding support for the "dependentSchemas" and "oneOf" keywords.
- Improved the efficiency & reliability of the company's fork of "React-Virtuoso" an open-source virtual infinite scrolling library for React.
  - URL: github.com/divar-ir/react-virtuoso forked from github.com/petyosi/react-virtuoso
  - Customized the library to suit the team's needs, considering critical non-functional requirements such as optimizing scrolling performance & data caching.
  - Improved functionality to prevent duplicate data requests and ensured that all pages displayed placeholders until the actual content was loaded.
  - Utilized the customized & improved version of React-Virtuoso on the main page of the company's website (e.g. divar.ir/s/tehran).
- Developed a fully-functional image slider/carousel from scratch using the DOM's mouse and touch APIs.
  - Implemented support for optional thumbnails and full-screen previews.
  - Adhered to responsive design as well as providing customization props to accommodate different sizes/aspect ratios.
  - Improved page load times by 10% by adding support for lazy-loading large images, where only a small blurred thumbnail was presented while the main image loaded in the background.

### **Lamasoo**

Mar 2018 - Aug 2018

#### Senior Back-End & Service Developer

5 months

- Contributed to the development of a "hotel channel-manager" API connecting travel agencies and websites
  to hotels for inquiring about room availability, rates, and making reservations.
- Developed a push API for transferring data from one service to another, utilized by several agencies
- Created a complex service for periodic polling of hotel data for preemptive requests of availability and rates
  - Implemented sliding-window techniques and multiple semaphores to prevent server congestion.
  - Designed a system for saving polled data in an SQL database for caching purposes and pushing updates to the travel agencies' web servers.
  - Optimized API code by incorporating cache, resulting in decreased response time from seconds to milliseconds

### **Dotin**

Sep 2015 - Sep 2017

#### Front-End Developer

2 vears

• Designed and developed home pages utilizing HTML/CSS/JavaScript, adhering to provided designs.

• Created reusable React components with TypeScript.

# **Technologies**



### Languages

Persian

Native

English

**IELTS:** 8.0 / 9.0 **TOEFL:** 113 / 120

### **Education**

University of Tehran

Sep 2016 - Jun 2019

M.S. in Software Engineering

University of Tehran

Sen 2011 - Jun 2016

B.S. in Software Engineering